{
  "title": "Discrete_Mathematics - Discrete_Mathematics — Slot 1 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Discrete_Mathematics — Slot 1",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>The unit interval \\((0, 1)\\) is divided at a point chosen uniformly distributed over \\((0,1)\\) in \\(\\mathbb{R}\\) into two disjoint subintervals. <br><br>The expected length of the subinterval that contains 0.4 is ___________. (rounded off to two decimal places) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "0.7",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460838/gate-cse-2025-set-2-question-55#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>A quadratic polynomial \\((x - \\alpha)(x - \\beta)\\) over complex numbers is said to be square invariant if \\((x - \\alpha)(x - \\beta) = (x - \\alpha^2)(x - \\beta^2)\\). Suppose from the set of all square invariant quadratic polynomials we choose one at random. <br><br>The probability that the roots of the chosen polynomial are equal is ______. (rounded off to one decimal place) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "0.5",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460839/gate-cse-2025-set-2-question-54#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(\\mathcal{F} \\) be the set of all functions from \\(\\{1, \\dots, n\\} \\) to \\(\\{0,1\\} \\). Define the binary relation \\(\\preceq \\) on \\(\\mathcal{F} \\) as follows:<br>\n\\(\n\\forall f, g \\in \\mathcal{F}, \\, f \\preceq g \\quad \\text{if and only if} \\quad \\forall x \\in \\{1, \\dots, n\\}, f(x) \\leq g(x), \\text{ where } 0 \\leq 1.\n\\)<br>\nWhich of the following statement(s) is/are TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\preceq \\) is a symmetric relation</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\((\\mathcal{F}, \\preceq) \\) is a partial order</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\((\\mathcal{F}, \\preceq) \\) is a lattice</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\preceq \\) is an equivalence relation</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\((\\mathcal{F}, \\preceq) \\) is a partial order</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\((\\mathcal{F}, \\preceq) \\) is a lattice</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460803/gate-cse-2025-set-2-question-32#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(P(x) \\) be an arbitrary predicate over the domain of natural numbers. Which ONE of the following statements is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\((P(0) \\land (\\forall x [P(x) \\Rightarrow P(x+1)])) \\Rightarrow (\\forall x P(x)) \\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\((P(0) \\land (\\forall x [P(x) \\Rightarrow P(x-1)])) \\Rightarrow (\\forall x P(x)) \\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\((P(1000) \\land (\\forall x [P(x) \\Rightarrow P(x-1)])) \\Rightarrow (\\forall x P(x)) \\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\((P(1000) \\land (\\forall x [P(x) \\Rightarrow P(x+1)])) \\Rightarrow (\\forall x P(x)) \\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\((P(0) \\land (\\forall x [P(x) \\Rightarrow P(x+1)])) \\Rightarrow (\\forall x P(x)) \\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460830/gate-cse-2025-set-2-question-5#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Consider a probability distribution given by the density function \\( P(x) \\).\n<br><br>\n\\( P(x) =\n\\begin{cases}\nCx^2, &amp;\\text{for   } 1 \\leq x \\leq 4 \\\\\n0, &amp;   \\text{for   }x &lt; 1 \\text{ or } x &gt; 4\n\\end{cases}\\)\n<br><br>\nThe probability that \\( x \\) lies between 2 and 3, i.e., \\( P(2 \\leq x \\leq 3) \\) is _________. (rounded off to three decimal places) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "0.3",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460032/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-48#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Suppose a 5-bit message is transmitted from a source to a destination through a noisy channel. The probability that a bit of the message gets flipped during transmission is 0.01. Flipping of each bit is independent of one another. The probability that the message is delivered error-free to the destination is _________. (rounded off to three decimal places) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "0.949",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460034/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-46#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>\\( A = \\{ 0,1,2,3,\\dots \\} \\) is the set of non-negative integers. Let \\( {F} \\) be the set of functions from \\( A \\) to itself. For any two functions, \\( f_1, f_2 \\in {F} \\), we define\n<br><br>\n\\( (f_1 \\odot f_2)(n) = f_1(n) + f_2(n)\\)\n<br><br>\nfor every number \\( n \\) in \\( A \\). Which of the following is/are CORRECT about the mathematical structure \\( ({F}, \\odot ) \\)? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\( ({F}, \\odot ) \\) is an Abelian group.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\( ({F}, \\odot ) \\) is an Abelian monoid.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\( ({F}, \\odot ) \\) is a non-Abelian group.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\( ({F}, \\odot ) \\) is a non-Abelian monoid.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\( ({F}, \\odot ) \\) is an Abelian monoid.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460041/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-39#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following predicate logic formulae/formula is/are CORRECT representation(s) of the statement: \"Everyone has exactly one mother\"?\n<br><br>The meanings of the predicates used are:\n<br>\n\\(mother(y,x): y\\) is the mother of \\( x \\)\n<br>\\(noteq(x,y): x\\) and  \\( y \\) are not equal <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\( \\forall x \\exists y \\exists z (mother(y, x) \\land \\neg mother(z, x)) \\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\( \\forall x \\exists y [mother(y, x) \\land \\forall z (noteq(z, y) \\to \\neg mother(z, x))] \\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\( \\forall x \\forall y [mother(y, x) \\to \\exists z (mother(z, x) \\land \\neg noteq(z, y))] \\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\( \\forall x \\exists y [mother(y, x) \\land \\neg \\exists z (noteq(z, y) \\land mother(z, x))] \\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\( \\forall x \\exists y [mother(y, x) \\land \\forall z (noteq(z, y) \\to \\neg mother(z, x))] \\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\( \\forall x \\exists y [mother(y, x) \\land \\neg \\exists z (noteq(z, y) \\land mother(z, x))] \\)</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460042/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-38#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>A box contains 5 coins: 4 regular coins and 1 fake coin. When a regular coin is tossed, the probability \\(P(\\text{head}) = 0.5\\) and for a fake coin, \\(P(\\text{head}) = 1\\). You pick a coin at random and toss it twice, and get two heads. The probability that the coin you have chosen is the fake coin is _______. (rounded off to two decimal places) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "0.49",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460058/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-22#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(S\\) be the set of all ternary strings defined over the alphabet \\(\\{a, b, c\\}\\). Consider all strings in \\(S\\) that contain at least one occurrence of two consecutive symbols, that is, \"aa\", \"bb\" or \"cc\". The number of such strings of length 5 that are possible is _______. (Answer in integer) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "195",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460060/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-20#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>\\(g(. )\\) is a function from \\(A\\) to \\(B\\), \\(f(. )\\) is a function from \\(B\\) to \\(C\\), and their composition defined as \\(f(g(. ))\\) is a mapping from \\(A\\) to \\(C\\). <br>If \\(f(. )\\) and \\(f(g(. ))\\) are onto (surjective) functions, which ONE of the following is TRUE about the function \\(g(. )\\)? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(g(. )\\) must be an onto (surjective) function.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(g(. )\\) must be a one-to-one (injective) function.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(g(. )\\) must be a bijective function, that is, both one-to-one and onto.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(g(. )\\) is not required to be a one-to-one or onto function.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(g(. )\\) is not required to be a one-to-one or onto function.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460073/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-7#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Let \\( Z_n \\) be the group of integers \\( \\{0,1,2, \\ldots, n-1\\} \\) with addition modulo \\( n \\) as the group operation. The number of elements in the group \\( Z_2 \\times Z_3 \\times Z_4 \\) that are their own inverses is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "4",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422844/gate-cse-2024-set-2-question-53#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>The chromatic number of a graph is the minimum number of colours used in a\nproper colouring of the graph. The chromatic number of the following graph\nis _______<br><img style=\"max-width:50%;height:auto;border-radius:8px;\" data-lazyloaded=\"1\" decoding=\"async\" src=\"images\\gatePYQ\\Discrete_Mathematics\\q50_6bd60b4f.webp\"><br> <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "2",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422847/gate-cse-2024-set-2-question-50#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Let \\( P \\) be the partial order defined on the set \\( \\{1,2,3,4\\} \\) as follows\n<br> \\(\nP=\\{(x, x) \\mid x \\in\\{1,2,3,4\\}\\} \\cup\\{(1,2),(3,2),(3,4)\\}\n\\) <br>\nThe number of total orders on \\( \\{1,2,3,4\\} \\) that contain \\( P \\) is ______ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "5",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422873/gate-cse-2024-set-2-question-24#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>When six unbiased dice are rolled simultaneously, the probability of getting all\ndistinct numbers (i.e., 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6) is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{1}{324}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{5}{324}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{7}{324}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{11}{324}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{5}{324}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422889/gate-cse-2024-set-2-question-8#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}